this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se - radio dotnet
I see radio brings you relevant detailed
discussions about software engineering
topics at least once a month
thanks to our audience and the partners
listed on our website for supporting the
podcast
[Music]
welcome to a new show and software
engineering radio my name is Michael and
my guest today is you can app hello we
are talking about leading a child
developers you can when I read about
articles about you you describe yourself
as being a leader a developer but not a
consultant but also author
so how would how would you introduce
yourself and what are you actually well
I've been a manager for 15 years I don't
do that anymore since few months I
switch to training and writing about
management and leadership to try and
help other people to do it well but as
you said that I do not do coaching or
console to see because I believe other
people are better at that than I am
I'm personally I prefer the writing and
and the training and what we are talking
about today is your latest book and I
guess it's also your first book as far
as I know is that right yes and yes
that's true the book is called HR
management 3.0 management 3.0 yeah good
so what is the book about in three
sentences before we go into more detail
on the book there are a number of books
about agile software development many
actually but most of them are for
sovereign Avella pers or project
managers or testers and this is I
believe the first one that really
tackles the role of the line manager and
team leader in an agile organization
okay and I mean looking at your history
and looking at a title you must have
felt that the urgent need to communicate
on that aspect and to basically share
your experiences
yes because as research points out that
agile has some difficulty being accepted
in many organizations because of the
responsibilities of management not being
clear
usually managers are seen as impediments
in scrum teams for example or agile
teams in general and I think managers
are not just impediments they have an
important role to play in changing and
transitioning the organization to agile
could you briefly elaborate your own
experiences your history as a manager as
a developer in HL organizations sure I
started out as a software developer and
then quickly ended up in management
positions and because I never learned
how to be a manager I basically did it
wrong in every way that I could so it
took me a while to learn how to do it
right this was this dystopia number of
years and at the same time I was
learning about agile sort of elements
and a number of years ago I decided to
introduce scrum in the organization that
I was managing at the time as CIO chief
information officer so that was a
decision by me as as a manager in the
organization and I believe by then I had
learned the through trial and error what
the role of the manager could be and
that's when I decided to start writing
about it you say you you did learn how
to do it right so how did you know that
you did it right I think one of the best
compliments I got when I quit my recent
job is that a former team member said to
me I never really saw you as my manager
I saw you as a colleague who made sure
that I could do my best job and this is
I believe exactly what a manager should
do shoot should go out of his way to to
make sure the team's can do the best
possible job
and that is I think the purpose of a of
a manager good so you you call it three
thought oh now we live in the age of web
2.0 by why did you call it 3.0 well it
started out as a tongue-in-cheek title
because as you said there's web 2.0
actually there's already web 3.0 and
there's motivation 3.0 and I thought it
would be fun to have a book title with a
version number in it because I wanted to
appeal to software developers and I said
jokingly that's that's why it has to
have a version number but there's also a
sort of philosophy behind it which is
that the first version of management as
far as I see it was his traditional
command and control management as as it
is still being practiced in many
organizations and the second version of
management is consists of all the fads
and and hypes we've seen the past few
decades that are well that have a lot of
usefulness in them but people try to
apply them to that old architecture of
traditional command and control
hierarchies which means it doesn't
really work that well and in my opinion
as I call it management 3.0 is the first
version of management with a good
architecture which is that the
organization is a network and not a
command and control hierarchy and if
you've seen the organization as a social
network then then you can reuse all
those previous best practices that have
usefulness but apply them in a more
modern fashion and that's what I call
management 3.0 okay so does management
3.0 basically build on 2.0 or such as
totally radically different from what
everything was before management could
practice no it is it is not totally
radically different because many people
have
applied very useful practices over the
last few decades and they're all still
valuable but if you apply them in an
organization that is is lead in a
command-and-control fashion then those
best practices have a very hard time of
actually working properly so that's
that's how I see it it is management 3.0
is not a collection of brand new
radically innovative practices it is
just common sense
applied in in a way that is that that
that is working well in 21st century
with an organization as a network
instead of a instead of a hierarchy so
some people might call some of the the
practices in the book not new but that's
because they're their common sense and I
just show them in in a new jacket so to
speak why is a child development so
different or are the people their
friends today I mean thirty years ago
twenty years ago we had also software
development we had successful software
development so did the big did the
change to management we all come through
HL development or what what made it know
is so important I think we have to
distinguish two different developments
in the last number of decades the first
one was about computer programming in
general which started out as a sort of
anarchistic way of trying to make sure
that computers did what we wanted from
the 50s and onwards and then in the 80s
software engineering was born in as a
response to the cowboy style of coding
that the universities tried to turn it
into something that was more structured
more formal and I've been raised as a
software engineer myself
a university degree so I so I know what
it looked like and yes as you said there
has been second there having successful
Pro software in the past both with
cowboy programming and artistic
programming and with the structured
formal approach but as your sub
developments in at the end of the 90s
early 2000s realized that there is a
middle road a middle road between
anarchy and and and order and that is a
complexity this this nicely aligns with
with complexity science one of my
favorite topics which says that that the
real innovation lies between the ordered
and the chaotic systems and that is
where the living systems are the the
ones that grow from bottom up and this
is exactly what you read also in in the
first books on agile software
development where they refer to
complexity sciences as one of the
sources of inspiration for therefore the
agile leaders at that time because
software development is more a social
thing as something which you can 100%
strictly blend in that meaning exactly
yes because a software project can be
seen as a living system with with
participants that all are in there for
their own purposes but try to cooperate
and produce some output and that is what
what complex systems tend tends to do it
is not a machine that you can that you
control from from from from the top it
is if you see it as a living system it
is much for your much more useful in
your book you introduce six distinct
views should we go briefly over each of
those views yes sure I have I have six
views mentioned in my in my book and the
first one is energized people this is
the first responsibility of development
managers and team leaders to make sure
that that people are in a project or in
teams
energized the second one is empower
teams which is about making sure that
self-organization works that people have
authority to make decisions themselves
the third one is align constraints which
is about setting goals to make sure that
self-organization leads to results that
are valuable for for the business the
fourth one is develop competence aligned
with with the craftsmanship movement for
example which which is about people
developing them themselves the fifth one
is gross structure which recognizes that
teams operate within the context of an
organization and you may have multiple
teams that have some relationship with
each other so you have to think about
the structure of the organization and
the last one is improve everything about
continuous improvement of not just of
processes but also of people
functionality quality and everything in
the energized people view you talk about
do-it-yourself
team values how did you come up with
that there are a number of values in
agile and in the scrum and extreme
programming methods for example where
they mention courage focus openness
respect Trust as basic values of agile
teams and when I researched these words
I found out that these are actually all
virtues of human beings and there are
many more virtues like assertiveness
caution enthusiasm curiosity persistence
thoroughness etc etc and I thought well
many of those virtues are very
beneficial in an agile setting and I
realized that the ones that should have
the most attention probably depend on
the context of the team like for example
in my last software team we
we didn't have any problems with respect
and Trust there was lots of respect and
Trust in the team but we did need a
little bit more orderliness and
self-discipline for example so I thought
well maybe we should have the the the
the all the virtues listed and asked
teams to circle the ones that that they
struggle with or that they think are
important for their current project in
their current context and then focus on
those so that might it might depend on
the team which ones are important ok so
it's not as a team exercise where to
focus the team with its values exactly
we did that ourselves we which we took
the list of 50 virtues and with the with
with top voting we made sure that we
aligned on them on the five or seven
virtues that we thought were most
important to us for our project and a
few of them were exactly the same as in
agile and a few were difference but we
found them to be important
next is empower teams what is important
about a 10 intrinsic desires well there
are lots of lots of theories about
intrinsic desires and the
self-determination theory is one and the
16 basic desires is another one and
basically it boils down to the fact that
as with values desires may differ per
person so for example some people need
orderliness in their environments they
are in need of structure while others
like me for example I thrive in in
Anarchy I love things not to be too
structured around me and this is it is
the same for other desires like some
people care very much about status while
others don't think that is important at
all
and I think managers can take those
differences into account and and align
the work that people do with what what
what is important to them if if a person
really needs orderliness for example
maybe that person would love to take
take care of the wiki pages where the
team process are described or something
like that this this could be taken up by
the team themselves but team members
themselves through self-organization but
a manager could also make sure that that
what they're what people are doing is
aligned with with with how they are
aligned is this the right keyword for
the third view aligned constraints what
are your tips for defining goals
I think goals and purpose are treated
somewhat simplistically in a number of
management books if you consider a
software team as a as a living system as
I prefer to do then I can only conclude
that there are different kinds of
purposes and there is for example a
difference between an emergent purpose
goal that a team themselves come up with
and an extrinsic purpose which is a goal
that a manager assigns to a team and
then there are the purposes of the
individual stakeholders like a product
owner has a purpose and this and and and
the customer has a purpose and
individual employees have their purposes
and suppliers have a purpose so there
are many kinds of goals and purposes and
I believe this what it is it makes sense
to to distinguish between a purpose data
that a manager assigns to a team like
for example we have to be profitable
next year with our product otherwise
we're out of business
and at the same time the team themselves
can come up with a purpose like we want
to be the best performing extreme
programming team in our company and
these should go hand in hand it is the
same as raising children where parents
have have had a purpose for the children
otherwise they will never had children
but at the same time the children grow
up and define purposes for themselves
and these have to align with each other
so the company would have to allow the
development team to define at least part
of its purpose right yes exactly because
it is a living system it has a reason
for existence and we call it emergence
when a self-organizing system comes up
with properties at at the system level
and the purpose of a listen living
system is typically an emergent property
it you cannot predict what it is but it
is there in the interaction between the
team members and any purpose that the
team comes up with comes up with has to
be evaluated with the manager and and
hopefully it can be aligned with with
the purpose that that management has for
therefore the teams that would be that
would be the best best outcome so it's
all said it's the the right thing but
how do you convince your environment
that letting the team define part of the
purpose is a good thing well how do you
define that a child can have its own
purpose in life that that just happens
if you ignore that that your children
have their own reasons for existence and
you basically instruct them and tell
them what to do they won't be happy in
the long run they may do what you want
in a short while in short well but but
in the long run you will you will lose
their commitment this is exactly what
happens with many software teams if they
just get told what to do you lose their
long-term commitment so I believe it is
important to accept that a team may have
a purpose of their own if you want to
have a
a sustainable software development
environment okay develop competence I
mean how do you know what to develop as
a manager how would you identify
competence gaps I think it is important
to have some form of measurements it is
very difficult to come up with good
measurements measurements and KPIs are
often used in very wrong in wrong ways
incorrect metrics but this it is crucial
to know how to do better by by tracking
how you're doing
like if you're exercising then you're
probably tracking your your your heart
rate or the number of kilometres that
you ran or the number of push-ups if you
don't and then how will you know how to
do better or if you did better than
before so this is basically measuring
yourself it is what what scrum teams do
and when they track velocity or when
they have when they attract buck count
or whatever it is it is evaluating their
own their own performance and that's why
it starts coming up with with good
metrics that align with the purpose of
the team and of management and then try
to understand what to do to do to be
better next time under the view of
growth structure you mentioned the term
value network what is a value network
well this is another example of of how
what it means to see an organization as
a complex system because the usual words
in agile development and in lean
development are value streams and value
stream mapping and value change for
example but these have linear
connotations the
they associated with with with linear
flow of value but if you see your
organization as a complex system then
you understand that value does not only
go in the direction of the customer
there's also suppliers and shareholders
and employees and the local community
where their business resides for which
the business supplies and employment so
there are many stakeholders in an
organization and they all try to draw
value out of that cooperation so if you
if you understand if you realize that
then you realize that it is not of one
value stream that you have you have a
value network with value going in in
different directions
and I see an organization as a number of
teams that all try to provide value to
each other and that value should end up
foul tamale at the customer site or with
the shareholders over the suppliers or
any of the other stakeholders next one
is improve everything what are the tips
for continuous improvement well sharpen
the saw we've learned already several
times now what do you recommend well if
we try to be concrete here there are a
number of tips from from other sources
that I that I collected like for example
to have an improvement backlog so not
only a backlog for your products that
you're working on but also a backlog for
for improvements of the team and the
organization that have a wider scope
than just the current project another
example is to have a transition team
consisting of people as representatives
of different roles and functions from
the organization where they lead the the
agile transition in the in the entire
organization another one is
well very popular these days is to have
Kanban boards for for product
developments where Kanban is actually a
continuous improvement framework that
through visualizing the flow of value
make sure that she that you see what
parts of the collaborating team needs to
be improved in order to make that value
flow faster so those are a few examples
of what you can do to improve your your
business okay so we covered all the six
views are there more views how how would
you know those you have those six this
is one way to categorize your
experiences yes my last chapter of the
book explains that in the end all models
are wrong but some are useful I find my
own model useful for now but probably I
will come up with what one or two views
later that I think I should have added
but we will see maybe maybe stakeholder
management's might be one that could be
turned into a seventh view at some point
in the future edition or something
looking at the introduction of eight hll
methodologies @hl mindset and and also
introducing your best practices it's
typically a larger transition that needs
to happen how would you help people to
move from an old-style management to a
more HR way I think one of the most
important things is to make things
visible this is exactly what what scrum
does for example it makes an aunt Condon
as well they make things visible by by
showing the work on a on a task boards
where a sticky notes flow from the left
to the right and as soon as you start
doing that you see what the bottlenecks
are
that that things are happening that that
you didn't that you didn't expect
etc etc and they call that visual
management scrum is is just one example
of visual management by making things
visible you make it you make it painful
and then there will be an urge to change
it and this is this is one of the most
important aspects of change management
in organizations to make things to make
things visible so if you start by that
you can do that with management as well
you can do that with with management as
well this probably is the this is the
first step to to begin with what will be
the second step the second step find
inspiration in by reading and going to
conferences etc because as my as my I
point out in my book there are no easy
solutions people regularly ask me for
for the silver bullets the the one or
the two simple things that you can do to
totally transform your organization and
that's not how it works every
organization is different every team is
different and you will have to adapt the
advice by others to your own context so
it is impossible to to tell people how
to start changing the organization
without any knowledge of their context
so my only advice is to is to make
things visible and and and learn by
reading and by seeing what others are
doing and adopt anything that makes
sense to you what are typical situations
where you think this management style
the management 3.0 style is not well
suited so when would you actually say
and recommend not to use this kind of
management style I think it is pretty
well suited for for many types of
organizations but it will be harder in
some of them like for example if you
have organizations were
tics are a very important part of what
is going on not only in political
parties but also in very traditional
bureaucratic organizations where
politics is an integral part of what is
happening then it it will be very hard
to implement the practices and the ideas
that that I describe in my book and
another situation might be where a
business is basically a one-man show one
person who has his own style and vision
etc on whatever needs to be produced and
just needs the help of few others that
might also not be a situation where some
of the practices are easily easily
applied because agile is is particularly
about teamwork and self-organizing teams
with little command and control from
from the top in my experience processes
are typically tightly aligned with
organization how you organize the teams
for example whether the team lead is
also the scrum master or not whether the
team lead leads or has a complete scrum
team or whether you have a matrix
organization where team lead would be
the manager of certain roles only I mean
there are certain cross influences
between an organization and a
methodology that the organization
employs now with this management style
you assume a certain process environment
I assume this is my assumption so what
are the organizational assumptions
basically
do you have actually I believe that that
it is the other way around that I
describe that every organization is
unique just like every every species in
nature is unique to its own environments
and as I have described you you cannot
tell that a starfish is better than a
spider because the starfish is the best
solution for for its environment in the
sea and the spider is the best solution
for its own environment in in my cellar
so it depends on on the context and the
same applies to processes as scrum
masters versus product owners and who
can do what and how teams need to be
aligned with other teams what kind of
structures day they have I give a number
of suggestions basically in my book that
that that work well in a number of
settings but I have a huge disclaimer in
the in the form of chapter 16 where I
say that where I have even have a
complexity pamphlet saying that in the
end it all depends on your own context
and you will have to just figure out by
trial and error what works for you
so never believe the fundamentalists who
say they have to do this because this is
the best practice there are no best
practices there are only useful
practices and please try them first
before you try the wrong because they
are not they are useful for a for a
reason but you might have situation that
is special to you so you will have to
adapt or invent your own so any
conclusions that you would like to share
at the end of our interview with our
listeners it is it is a difficult thing
to do to become a better manager better
software developer that's a project
manager
but but what what what I believe is
often the problem in in in many
organizations that few people learn few
people actually take the opportunity and
really pick up a book or or or a podcast
listen to a podcast or or download some
some movies from from from other from
other leaders and try to understand how
to be better at their jobs this is this
is what I've noticed many times that
people think they are already very
competent as they say 90% of the people
think they're competence is above
average well we all know this that that
formula doesn't work out so we all have
to keep learning how to be better okay
thank you Juergen for the interview and
bye-bye thank you very much for thanks
thanks for listening to software
engineering radio as a radio is an
educational program brought to you by
hillside Europe if you want more
information about the podcast and the
other episodes visit our website at SE -
radio dotnet if you want to support us
you can donate to the SA radio team by
at the website or you can advertise for
se radio for example by clicking on the
Digg reddit delicious and slash note
buttons or by talking about us on
Twitter and Facebook you can also
support us by joining team and
shouldering some of the work to contact
the team please send email to team at se
- radio net or if your feedback is
specific to an episode please use the
comments facility on the website so
other people can react to your comments
this episode of se radio as well as all
other episodes are licensed under a
creative commons 2.5 license please see
the website for details
[Music]